<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Harry VVhite his humour, so neare as may be set forth by M.P. In which is exprest, both earnest and jest: let honest men buy, and knaves let it lye: this is not for them, vvho vertue contemne[d]</title>
            <author>M. P. (Martin Parker), d. 1656?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08959</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119911</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855117</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20590</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08959)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20590)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1525:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Harry VVhite his humour, so neare as may be set forth by M.P. In which is exprest, both earnest and jest: let honest men buy, and knaves let it lye: this is not for them, vvho vertue contemne[d]</title>
                  <author>M. P. (Martin Parker), d. 1656?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Cotes?] for Thomas Lambert, at [the] signe of the Hors-shoo in Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1637]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Suggested printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>First and last leaves blank except for woodcut illustrations.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page cropped slightly affecting text and imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 95 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Harry White</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 95 -->
            <p>Harry VVhite his humour, So neare as may be ſet forth by M.P.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>In which is expreſt,</l>
               <l>Both earneſt and jeſt:</l>
               <l>Let honeſt men buy,</l>
               <l>And knaves let it lye:</l>
               <l>This is not for them,</l>
               <l>VVho vertue contemne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not every man in's humour's promis'd here,</l>
               <l>Yet in one's humour many more appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Thomas Lambert,</hi> at ſigne of the Horſ-ſhoo in Smithfield</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 96 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 96 -->
            <head>
               <l>To that great Promulgater,</l>
               <l>And neat divulgater,</l>
               <l>VVhom the citie admires,</l>
               <l>And the Suburbs deſires,</l>
               <l>M.P. wiſheth happy</l>
               <l>Succeſſe, and Ale nappy,</l>
               <l>That with the ones paine,</l>
               <l>He the other may gaine.</l>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honeſt Harry,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Aine I would ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yet I know not (nor indeed care not much) what to ſay to thee; I know thou art one armed for all ſayings. For to
<pb facs="tcp:20590:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 97 -->
ſpeake truly, praiſe of thee would bee counted but phantaſmie; and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion meere adulation: how canſt thou want worth, who haſt ſuch an ample faculty in emblazoning, and (indeed ſometimes) adding to the worth of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men? It likes my humour well to deſcribe thine ſo well as I could: the beſt on it is, thy humour is my privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; therefore if what is here writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſleightly, be ill read, and worſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, I can excuſe my ſelfe, (as many men doe their owne faults by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens) ſaying, it is Harry Whites humour. Surely I thinke I have fitted thy humour in generall, if not I pray thee let thy particular humour pardon eſcapes. I have aſſaid to humour thee, invited by this benefit, that by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring thee I ſhall humour a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand: now if any be in the humour to be vext at thy humour: tell them thy humour is armed againſt the aſſault
<pb facs="tcp:20590:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 97 -->
of any humour: thus wiſhing that thy humour may bee ſatisfied with tenne thouſand two peny cuſtomers, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee to thy humour, and thy hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to thy cuſtodie, deſiring ever to reſt, but never to be arreſted.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine at a pot and a pipe, M.P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 98 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 98 -->
            <head>Harry VVhites humour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ery good Sir, but why <hi>Harry Whites humour?</hi> pray what humour hath <hi>Harry White,</hi> that another man is not guilty of? why ſir to ſatisfie your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiue humour, Ile tell you what <hi>Harry Whites</hi> humour is: but before-hand I pray be not angry, yet if you be, <hi>Harry White</hi> cares not; that is part of his humour, he had rather ſée a whore want painting for her face than an honeſt. Woman want bread for her children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He had rather that théeues and cut-purſes (and conſequently the hangman) ſhould want employment than honeſt trades-men ſhould lack work or mony.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20590:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 99 -->
               <hi>Item</hi> He would haue fewer bawdy hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and more almeshouſes: alſo he wiſheth that rich people were more charitable: or that the poore had leſſe néede.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He can (when he is hungry) ver<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thankfully eate a red herring: but yet he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers a Hen or a Capon before it, and holds eyther of them to be better merit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He loues (and honors) all good qu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in men, yet he eſtéemes h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſty as the Maſter-p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He delights much to heare a good ring of Bells, yet he could wiſh rather to ſhew you a gold (or Diamond) Ring of his owne, though vpon another mans finger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He can (in caſe of neceſſity) drinke vpon frée coſt, yet he is better pleaſed when he hath mony to pay for his liquor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20590:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 99 -->
               <hi>Item</hi> He loues to ride when he is weary yet (at certaine times) he holds it ominous to ride <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Holborne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He is offended at nothing ſo as at ſwearing, curſing, or blaſphemy, eſpecially when an old hawd ſweares ſhe is an honeſt Woman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> Hée takes more pleaſure to ſée a Knight of the Poſt, play at boe péepe vpon a ſcaffold, than to behold a Carriers horſe to fall vnder his load.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He prefers a Cookes ſhop before a fencing ſchoole: and what is the reaſon think you? why, becauſe he had rather break his face than his head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He cares not much for a dancing-ſchoole, becauſe if néed be (rather than fall) he can eat Mutton without Capers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20590:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 100 -->
               <hi>Item</hi> He thinkes Millers and Mizers are more correſpondent in trade than in name: and why ſo? becauſe as the one grinde<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, the other grindes the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He troubles not his head much with learning Arithmeticke, for (when he is at the beſt) he can calculate his mony without eyther pen or Counters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> Of all men liuing he regards Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers. A reaſon for that prethée? why Ile tell you ſir their attractiue policy drawes him an Iron audience out of the Country: for hée thinkes it is neuer ſo well with <hi>London</hi> as when the hobnayles ſtrike fire out of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtones.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> It goes to his very heart to heare the man that cryes buy a bruſh, for it puts him in minde of his holy-day cloake that lies in Long-Lane to be bruſht: for though his kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery be but little, yet a ſtronger cloak would doe well to couer it, leaſt one that hath much
<pb facs="tcp:20590:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 100 -->
ſhould ſteale away his little: for now adayes no knauery no liuing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He is loath to marry a Widow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will not taſte of that which another man dyed after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He is confidently conceited that if all men would abſtain from immoderate drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, quarrelling, wenching, and gameing: Phiſitians, Surgeons, and catchpoles, ſhould haue farre leſſe employment than they haue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He is alſo verily perſwaded that if Women could but gouerne one little péece of fleſh (the tongue I meane) ſo many of them would not goe with party coulerd faces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He will not be troubled with paying Ale-houſe ſcores: no, no, he hath a fine trick to preuent that: as how ſir I prethée? why by calling in no more than he is able to pay for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20590:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 101 -->
               <hi>Item</hi> He ſcornes to be comited a ſhifting companion, for where he méetes with good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor and good company, he ſeldome departs willingly, vntill Peter pouerty puts him out of the doore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He hates of all (humane) things to be ouerſéene in bread: for he had rather the Brewer ſhould thriue than the Baker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He holds it neceſſary and conuenient, by order of equity (and indeed warranted by his owne exemplary practice) that he who is drunke ouer-night, ſhall (in ſatiſfaction to the Bachinalian ſtatute) pay a groaſ on the next morning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> Hauing lately read the rare hiſtory of patient <hi>Grizell,</hi> out of it he hath drawne this Phyloſophicall poſition, that if all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were of that Womans condition, we ſhould haue no imployment for cuckinſtooles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20590:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 101 -->
               <hi>Item</hi> He is of this opinion, that if the hiſtories of <hi>Garragantua</hi> and <hi>Tom Thumbe</hi> be true: by conſequence <hi>Bevis</hi> of <hi>Hampton,</hi> and <hi>Scoggins Jeſts</hi> muſt néedes bée Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He is an excellent Orator, and I think he carryes ſome glew vpon his tongue that joynes the eares of his auditors ſo faſt vnto him, that they cannot depart til they are pleaſed or vext: for you ſhall ſée the people flock about him, like Bées to a hony pot: hee tells them his minde, and is in a mannor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different whether they be angry or pleaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He hath more minde to goe to <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſgate</hi> to eate Oyſters, (though he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe friendſhip with a boxe on the eare) than to interpoſe himſelfe in an idle quarrel, when he may gaine a broken pate for his good will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He profeſſeth himſelfe an open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to double dealing, and yet in cold weather (prouided it be at your owne charges) you
<pb facs="tcp:20590:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 102 -->
may eaſily perſwade him to weare two ſhirts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He neuer will be ſparing in other mens praiſes, for he extolles a good worke (done by any man) to the higheſt: and this is not onely done in corners, for he tells it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in the ſtréetes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He is to much addicted (and that is both a mad humour, and a bad humour) to any Sycophants that will flatter his fancy: and by their tongues (being giulded with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit) draw ſiluer out of his pockets in expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry VVhites humour, by no wiſe man to be followed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He hath an admirable faculty in iudging the mindes of others, for if he ſées a maide of her owne accord to kiſſe a young man he dares almoſt be ſworne ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> loues him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20590:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 102 -->
               <hi>Item</hi> He holds it an odious object to ſée a man drunk: but a Woman to goe réeling in the ſtréetes, cut vpon her beaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> Beſides this, hée thinks it may bée probably conjectured (without any prejudice to art or nature) that a Woman who will be commonly drunk, doth now and then (when her ſenſes are intoxicated) miſtake another man for her husband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He loues good company with all his heart, and had rather ſpend a ſhilling on a good fellow, than a penny on a whore.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He cannot abide to whiſper out his minde, as though he were either affraid, or aſhamed of his profeſſion: no, no, you ſhall heare him, if you be neare him: he will not lack mony, if ſpeaking for it can procure it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He is ſeldome or neuer affraid of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſting: for pouerty preuents borrowing, and
<pb facs="tcp:20590:9"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 103 -->
if nothing be borrowed, there is nothing to pay: then a figge for the catchpole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He loues no kinde of gaming, his reaſon is this, that although the game of it ſelfe may be lawfull enough (being lawfully vſed for honeſt recreation) yet there are ſo many abſurdities and inconueniencies deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the ſame, (as ſwearing, curſing, quarrelling, betwéene neareſt friends: and many other euils) that he will not play with any man, no not for ſhooe-buckles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He holds it vnneceſſary that a horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſer and a broker ſhould dwell néere toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: why ſo ſir? why ſir, becauſe the prouerb ſayes, that a crafty knaue néedes no broker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He had rather ſée a pick-pocket car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to <hi>Newgate</hi> (looke to your purſes Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) than a poore man to the Compter for debt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry Whites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20590:9"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 103 -->
               <hi>Item</hi> He eſtéemes it a point of no good husbandry for any man to loyter and bee drinking all the working dayes, and to follow his labour on Sundayes, or holy-dayes: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he commend the cuſtome of thoſe Iourneymen, or labourers, who hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued their wages on the Saturday night, doe ſpend all (or the moſt part of it) on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day: and the next wéeke following are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to make more faſting-daies than the Church commands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> He déemes that a prepoſterous go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment where the wife predominates, and the husband ſubmits to her diſcretion; that is juſt <hi>Hyſtoron &amp; Proteron,</hi> the Cart before the horſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>A womans counſell's ofttimes fit,</l>
               <l>For many of them have ſudden wit:</l>
               <l>But where the wife beares greateſt ſway,</l>
               <l>That houſe can be at no good ſtay.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>This is Harry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> On the contrary he counts it a baſe inhumane part, for any man to beat his Wife: nay and beſides, it is an abſurd fully, for if ſhe be good, ill vſage may peruert her: if
<pb facs="tcp:20590:10"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 104 -->
ſhe be bad, blowes will not mend her: for being a weake veſſell ſhe will rather breake with beating: what a ſimplicity is it for a man (in his fury) to giue his Wife a blacke eye: and then to cogge and flatter, looke ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byes in her eyes, call her his pigges nye, and cry <hi>Peccavi</hi> (for his fault) a fortnight, or thrée wéekes after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is not Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Harry VVhite</hi> is glad at the heart to ſée the young men laughing, the maides ſmiling, ſome drawing their purſes, others groping in their pockets, ſome pretty laſſes feeling in their boſomes for odde parcells of mony wrapt in clouts: for theſe are euident preſages of his good fortune: ah what dulcid muſick it is to his eares, when he heares his audience cry, joyntly, giue me one, giue mee two: change my mony ſayes one, here is a ſingle two pence ſayes another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This fits Harry VVhites humour.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:10"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 104 -->
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>NOw worthy friends if what is here expreſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>of <hi>Harry White</hi> his humour, yours have pleaſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>The author and the Subject wil conteſt</l>
               <l>about their ſhares of Joy; yet ſoone appeaſd,</l>
               <l>Shall joyntly joyne in their congratulation,</l>
               <l>VVhile in your loves both hath participation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>IN his one humour many are compriz'd</l>
               <l>then take your choice, as every man ſhal fi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>In his owne heart: what here's epitomis'd,</l>
               <l>you may exemplifie in your owne mind.</l>
               <l>Let fame, (times harold) daign to blaze this rum<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>Harry whites</hi> not here, yet heres his humo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:11"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 105 -->
            <head>An applauſe by L.P. Of the Author M.P.</head>
            <l>THe Author of this little booke,</l>
            <l>which he in love hath pend,</l>
            <l>Is 'cauſe ſome may behold their faults,</l>
            <l>and practice to amend.</l>
            <l>He flatters not as many doe,</l>
            <l>to win himſelfe a praiſe,</l>
            <l>But boldly paints abuſes forth</l>
            <l>that's uſed now adaies</l>
            <l>'Mongſt men of ſound diſcretion, ſure</l>
            <l>theſe lines will breed no jarre,</l>
            <l>But it may make gauld jades to kick,</l>
            <l>becauſe they ſpurred are,</l>
            <l>The Author in a recompence,</l>
            <l>to them that angry be,</l>
            <l>Bequeaths a gift that's cald</l>
            <l>old Gillians legacie.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:20590:11"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 105 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Harry White</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
